Thank for you choosing to fly
with Oberth Aerospace today.
本日[ほんじつ]:today
（アナウンス）
本日は―
オーデルト
エアロスペースを―
利用[りよう]:use/utilization/utilisation, いただく:to receive/to get|to eat, 誠[まこと]:truth|sincerity|that's right (used when recalling forgotten information, suddenly changing the subject, etc.), ありがとう:Thank you/Thanks, ござる:to be
ご利用いただきまして
誠にありがとうございます
We departed from
the Bangkok airport on...
当[とう]:this (business organisation or place), 当[はた]:or|furthermore|perhaps||, 機[はた]:loom, 機[き]:chance|machine|aircraft||, 空[から]:emptiness/vacuum/blank, 空[そら]:sky|weather|far-off place||
当機は バンコス空…
（ナレーション）
２０６８年―
2068.
高[たか, だか]:quantity/amount/volume, 高[こう]:high school|high-, 高度[こうど]:altitude/height|high-degree, 旅客機[りょかくき, りょかっき]:passenger plane
高高度旅客機―
The accident with the Alnair 8
suborbital passenger liner...
型[かた, がた]:model|type|mold (mould)||, 事故[じこ, ことゆえ]:accident/incident|circumstances
アルナイル８型の
事故から―
...focused public attention on the problem
of space debris.
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space
宇宙のゴミ―
スペース:space (room, area, outer space), デブリ:debris, 問題[もんだい]:question (e.g. on a test)|problem (e.g. societal, political)|question (i.e. doubt)||
スペースデブリの
問題が―
大きい[おおきい]:big/large/great, クローズアップ:close-up
大きくクローズアップ
されるようになりました
Abandoned artificial satellites.
使い捨てる[つかいすてる]:to use and then throw away, 人工衛星[じんこうえいせい]:man-made satellite
使い捨てられた人工衛星
Tanks jettisoned from shuttles.
シャトル:shuttlecock, 切り離す[きりはなす]:to detach/to decapitate/to cut loose, タンク:tank (of liquid)
シャトルが切り離したタンク
Refuse generated during
space station construction.
ステーション:station, 建造[けんぞう]:building/construction, 廃棄物[はいきぶつ]:waste matter/waste/garbage
ステーション建造時に出た廃棄物
デブリ:debris
これらのデブリは―
This debris is traveling around the Earth at speeds
approaching eight kilometers per second.
秒速[びょうそく]:per second, キロメートル:kilometer/kilometre, 近い[ちかい]:near|close (in time)|close (relationship)||, 速度[そくど]:speed/velocity/rate, 地球[ちきゅう]:the earth/the globe, 周り[まわり]:circumference/girth|surroundings, 回る[めぐる]:to go around|to return|to surround|, 回る[まわる]:to turn|to visit several places|to function well|
秒速８キロメートル近い速度で
地球の周りを回っています
Should this debris collide with a spacecraft,
it could result in a terrible accident.
デブリ:debris, 宇宙船[うちゅうせん]:space ship, ぶつかる:to strike against/to collide with|to encounter
そんなデブリは
宇宙船とぶつかれば―
大きな[おおきな]:big/large/great, 事故[じこ, ことゆえ]:accident/incident|circumstances, つながる:to be tied together/to be connected to|to lead to, かねる:to be unable to/to find difficult (unpleasant, awkward, painful) to do|to serve two or more functions or roles simultaneously
大きな事故に つながりかねません
悲劇[ひげき]:tragedy/tragic drama|tragedy, 繰り返す[くりかえす]:to repeat/to do something over again
そこで
悲劇を繰り返さないため―
And so, to prevent such a tragedy
from ever happening again,
...as well as for the sake of
further space development,
更なる[さらなる]:even more/still more/further, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 開発[かいはつ, かいほつ]:development/exploitation
そして
更なる宇宙開発のためにも―
...disposal of this debris
has become a necessity.
デブリ:debris, 処理[しょり]:processing/dealing with/treatment, 必要[ひつよう]:necessary/needed|necessity
デブリの処理が
必要になってきました
時代[じだい]:period|the times|oldness|, 生きる[いきる]:to live|to make a living|to be in effect||, 人々[ひとびと, にんにん]:each person/people/men and women, 物語[ものがたり]:tale/story/legend
これは そんな時代に
生きる人々の物語
This is a story of the people
who live in such a time as this.
♪～
Phase 1
Outside the Atmosphere
（管制官）GOS-09…
GO-S09, routing from exposed area to Bay Five.
Main umbilical, connection complete.
I'm in space...
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space
（タナベ）宇宙だ
やっと:at last/at length|barely, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 勤務[きんむ]:service/duty/work
（タナベ）
やっと来た！ 宇宙勤務
I finally got a space assignment!
間[あいだ, あわい]:space (between)|time (between)|span (temporal or spatial)||, 間[ま]:time|space|room, 社[やしろ]:shrine (usually Shinto), 社[しゃ]:company|regional Chinese god of the earth (or a village built in its honour)|counter for companies, shrines, etc.
（アナウンス）
間もなく テクノーラ社―
Next stop, Technora Corporation
office block.
オフィス:office, ブロック:to block (e.g. the way)
オフィスブロックです
無重力[むじゅうりょく]:weightlessness/zero gravity, 衛星[えいせい]:satellite, 軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 飛行士[ひこうし]:pilot
（タナベ）
無重力 衛星軌道 宇宙飛行士
Zero-G... Satellite orbit...
Astronauts!
えっ…
Oh, right.
That's our mascot character...
マスコット:mascot, キャラ:(fictional) character
そっか マスコットキャラ
Excuse me!
失礼[しつれい, しつらい]:discourtesy|Excuse me|to leave|
（タナベ）失礼します！
（クレア）ん？
度[たび, たんび]:time (three times, each time, etc.)/times, 度[ど]:degree (angle, temperature, scale, etc.)|counter for occurrences and times|strength (of alcohol), 第[だい]:prefix for forming ordinal numbers, 事業部[じぎょうぶ]:division (of company)/operations department, デブリ:debris, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 配属[はいぞく]:assignment (of a person to somewhere)/attachment (of a person to another unit, organization, etc.), 愛[あい]:love/affection|attachment, 愛[まな]:beloved/dear
私 この度 第２事業部デブリ課に
配属となりました 田名部(たなべ) 愛(あい)です
I am Ai Tanabe, newly assigned to
Second Department, Debris Section!
Age 20, single, Japanese!
I look forward to working with you!
歳[さい]:-years-old|ability/gift, 歳[とし]:year|age|past one's prime, 独身[どくしん]:bachelorhood/single/unmarried, 日本人[にほんじん, にっぽんじん]:Japanese person/Japanese people, よろしく:well/properly|best regards, 願う[ねがう]:to desire|to beg|to have something done for oneself
20歳 独身 日本人
よろしく お願いします！
えーっと:let me see/well/errr ...
（タナベ）えーっと…
Um...
社内[しゃない]:within a company/in-house, 配置[はいち]:arrangement (of resources)/deployment/stationing, ぐらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that
（ドルフ）
社内の配置ぐらい―
At least learn where things are in the company.
覚える[おぼえる]:to memorize|to learn|to feel|, なさる:to do, 管制[かんせい]:control, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book)
覚えておきなさい
ここは管制課だ
This is Control Section.
あっ あれ？ すいません
Huh? It is?
Oh, I'm sorry!
うわっ うわっ えっ…
ああ… ああ…
Claire, we'll wait until we get instructions
from INTO to deal with that plate.
プレート:plate (often as in "tectonic plate"), 関する[かんする]:to concern/to be related, 連合[れんごう]:union/alliance|RENGO (Japanese Trade Union Confederation), 指示[しじ, しし]:indication/denotation|instructions, 待ち[まち]:waiting/waiting time
クレア君 そのプレートに関しては
連合の指示待ちとする
分かりました
Understood, sir.
すいません どうも ああっ…
I'm really sorry... Thank you.
まったく:really/truly|indeed, 半[はん]:half|half-past|odd number|, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 新人[しんじん]:new face/newcomer|modern humans (from Cro-Magnon man onwards), らしい:seeming ... (expresses judgment based on evidence, reason or trustworthy hearsay)/appearing ...|-ish
（クレア）
まったく 半課の新人らしいわ
Good grief... You must be a new
recruit for the Half Section.
Half Section?
No, ma'am, Debris Section.
半[はん]:half|half-past|odd number|, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), デブリ:debris
（タナベ）
半課？ いえ デブリ課ですけど
Like I said, Half Section.
半[はん]:half|half-past|odd number|, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book)
（クレア）だから 半課でしょ
半[はん]:half|half-past|odd number|, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 社内[しゃない]:within a company/in-house, エレベーター:elevator/lift, 一番[いちばん]:number one|best|game||, 一番[ひとつがい]:pair/couple/brace
半課なら
社内エレベーターで 一番下
If you're looking for Half Section, take the
company elevator all the way to the bottom.
（リュシー）
何やってんの タナベ
What were you thinking, Tanabe?
管制[かんせい]:control, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 書く[かく]:to write/to compose|to draw
（シャポウ）
管制課って書いてあるじゃない
"Control Section" is written there
as plain as day!
You could've said something,
you know...
教える[おしえる]:to teach|to tell|to preach
教えてくれればいいのに
That's what you get for trying
to make a grand entrance!
あんまり:remainder/rest|not very (with negative sentence), 堂々[どうどう]:magnificent|fair|grandly|
（リュシー）だって あんまり
堂々と入っていくからさあ
Say, wasn't that the guy who gave the speech
at our company welcoming ceremony?
入社式[にゅうしゃしき]:(company's) initiation or welcoming ceremony, 挨拶[あいさつ]:greeting|polite set phrase used to express apology, sympathy, congratulations, etc.|speech (congratulatory or appreciative)||
（ヴァンリ）ねえ 今のって
入社式で挨拶してた人？
Right, he's the
department manager.
事業部長[じぎょうぶちょう]:senior executive manager
（シャポウ）
そうそう 事業部長さん
減点[げんてん]:subtract/give a demerit
ええっ！？
（リュシー）減点１だね
One point deduction,
looks like.
研修[けんしゅう]:training (esp. in-service)/induction course, 成績[せいせき]:results/record/grades, 良い[よい]:good|sufficient (can be used to turn down an offer)|profitable (e.g. deal, business offer, etc.)|
（タナベ）ああっ ただでさえ
研修の成績 良くなかっ…
It's not like my workshop grades
were all that great...
- Look out!
危ない[あぶない]:dangerous|in danger|uncertain||, 最下位[さいかい]:lowest rank/bottom|least significant (bit)
（リュシー）
危ないっ！ そんなんだから
最下位になっちゃうのよ
Sheesh, this is why
you're at the bottom of the class.
（タナベ）うん？
社内[しゃない]:within a company/in-house, ダンス:dance, 大会[たいかい]:convention/tournament/mass meeting, 準優勝[じゅんゆうしょう]:being the runner-up/finishing second
（シャポウ）
でも 社内ダンス大会では
準優勝でしょ？
Maybe, but she came in second at the Technora
company dance competition, remember?
Dance?
ダンス:dance
（ヴァンリ）ダンス？
Sure, you remember.
社[やしろ]:shrine (usually Shinto), 社[しゃ]:company|regional Chinese god of the earth (or a village built in its honour)|counter for companies, shrines, etc., 企業[きぎょう]:enterprise/undertaking/corporation, 精神[せいしん]:mind/soul/heart
ほら あれよ
テクノーラ社の企業精神を―
The one where you're supposed to express your Technora company spirit through original dance.
創作[そうさく]:production/literary creation/work, ダンス:dance, 表現[ひょうげん]:expression/presentation|representation
創作ダンスで
表現しましょうってやつ
Only two of us entered.
応募[おうぼ]:application/subscription/entry (competition, raffle, etc.)
（タナベ）
応募したの２人だけだった
（シャポウ）えっ そうなの？
Oh, really?
Who in their right mind would sign up
for something that embarrassing?
あんな:such (about something or someone distant from both speaker and listener, or about a situation unfamiliar to both speaker and listener)/so/that, あんな:Anna or Anwa era (968.8.13-970.3.25), 恥ずかしい[はずかしい]:shy/ashamed|disgraceful, 応募[おうぼ]:application/subscription/entry (competition, raffle, etc.)
（リュシー）あんな恥ずかしいの
誰も応募しないって
よく出たよね
I'm amazed you entered!
Look, I joined by walking in off the street
and I've got no connections,
一般[いっぱん]:general/universal|ordinary, 入社[にゅうしゃ]:joining a company/getting a job with a company/entering a company
だってさ
私 一般入社でコネもないし―
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space
でも 宇宙には出てみたかったし
だから…
...but I wanted to try to go
into space, so I signed up for it.
See you later, Tanabe.
航宙[こうちゅう]:space flight, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 左[ひだり]:left/left hand side, 左[さ]:left (esp. in vertical Japanese writing)/the following
（リュシー）じゃあね タナベ
航宙課は 左のほうだから
Aerospace Section
is to the left, so this is my stop.
Maintenance Section, too.
整備[せいび]:maintenance/servicing|putting in place, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book)
整備課もだ
I guess this is goodbye
for now.
一旦[いったん]:once|for a short time|one morning, 別れ[わかれ]:parting/separation/farewell
ここで 一旦 お別れだね
That's the elevator that will
take you down, Tanabe.
降りる[おりる]:to descend (e.g. a mountain)|to alight (e.g. from bus)|to step down||
タナベは そこから降りるんだよ
子供[こども]:child/children
もう！ 子供じゃないんだから
Come on,
I'm not a kid!
Be careful.
気をつける[きをつける]:to be careful/to pay attention/to take care
（ヴァンリ）気をつけて
Of what?
何を？
つぼね:court lady/lady-in-waiting (Heian period)|separate room in a palace (esp. for a lady) (Heian period), セクハラ:sexual harassment, おやじ:first character (of a dictionary entry), おやじ:one's father/old man/one's boss, 逆らう[さからう]:to go against/to oppose/to disobey
（ヴァンリ）
おつぼねや セクハラおやじに
会っても 逆らわない
If you run into any drama queens
or dirty old men, don't fight back.
'Cause you always act
before thinking.
考える[かんがえる]:to think about|to ponder|to intend||, 行動[こうどう]:action/conduct/behaviour
（シャポウ）あんたは
考える前に 行動しちゃうから
She doesn't pay attention
to her surroundings, either.
あまり:remainder/rest|not very (with negative sentence), 周り[まわり]:circumference/girth|surroundings, 見える[みえる]:to be seen|to look|to come, 見える[まみえる]:to have an audience|to face (an enemy)|to serve (esp. as one's wife)
（リュシー）
あまり周りも見えてないしね
I don't?
（タナベ）そうかなあ
No, you don't.
昼[ひる]:noon|daytime|lunch
（シャポウ）そうなの
（ヴァンリ）じゃあ お昼に
See you
at lunch, then.
Remember, Debris Section
is downstairs.
デブリ:debris, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book)
（リュシー）
デブリ課は 下だからね
しつこい:insistent/obstinate|too rich (taste, etc.)
しつこい！
Lay off!
デブリ:debris, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 一番[いちばん]:number one|best|game||, 一番[ひとつがい]:pair/couple/brace
（タナベ）デブリ課は 一番下
一番下 一番下…
Debris Section is all
the way at the bottom...
All the way at the bottom...
All the way at the bottom is Debris Section.
一番[いちばん]:number one|best|game||, 一番[ひとつがい]:pair/couple/brace, デブリ:debris, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book)
一番下は デブリ課
Yep, this is it,
all right.
間違い[まちがい]:mistake|accident|improper conduct (e.g. between man and woman)
うん！ 間違いなし
Starting today,
this is my workplace.
職場[しょくば]:one's post/place of work/workplace
今日から ここが私の職場なんだ
失礼[しつれい, しつらい]:discourtesy|Excuse me|to leave|
よっし 失礼します！
Let's do it!
Excuse me! I've just been assigned to
Second Department, Debris... Section?
度[たび, たんび]:time (three times, each time, etc.)/times, 度[ど]:degree (angle, temperature, scale, etc.)|counter for occurrences and times|strength (of alcohol), 第[だい]:prefix for forming ordinal numbers, 事業部[じぎょうぶ]:division (of company)/operations department, デブリ:debris, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 配属[はいぞく]:assignment (of a person to somewhere)/attachment (of a person to another unit, organization, etc.)
私 この度
第２事業部デブリ課に配属…
♪～
間違える[まちがえる]:to make a mistake (in)/to commit an error (e.g. in calculation)|to confuse
（タナベ）
ま… 間違えました すいません
I-I've made a mistake!
Pardon me!
But this is Debris Section...
デブリ:debris, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book)
デブリ課だよね？ ここ
えーっと:let me see/well/errr ...
えーっと…
Um...
たびたび:often/again and again/over and over again, 恐れ入る[おそれいる]:to be sorry|to be grateful|to be amazed|, デブリ:debris, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book)
たびたび恐れ入ります
デブリ課は…
I'm sorry to keep bothering you,
but where is Debris...
半[はん]:half|half-past|odd number|, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book)
（ハチマキ）
半課 半課って うるせえんだよ！
I've had it up to here with their
"Half Section" crap!
うわあっ だっだっだっ…
課長[かちょう]:section manager/section chief, 管制[かんせい]:control, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 後[あと]:behind|after|after one's death||, 後[のち]:later|future|after one's death|
（ハチマキ）課長！ どうして
うちが管制課の後なんだよ！
Dammit, Chief, how come we always
play second fiddle to Control Section?!
あっち:that way (direction distant from both speaker and listener)/over there|that one (something physically distant from both speaker and listener, or something not visible but known by both speaker and listener), 人数[にんずう, ひとかず]:the number of people|many people/a large number of people
（課長）だって
あっちのほうが人数も多いし
Well, they have a bigger staff
than we do.
宇宙服[うちゅうふく]:space suit
（ハチマキ）やつらは
宇宙服だって使わないだろうが！
Those guys don't even
use spacesuits!
An astronaut...
A real astronaut...!
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 飛行士[ひこうし]:pilot, 本物[ほんもの]:genuine article/real thing/real deal
宇宙飛行士… 本物だ
Huh? Who are you?
（ハチマキ）あ？ 誰だ？ お前
おむつ:diaper/nappy/napkin
あっ おむつ！
Diapers?
Hey, don't blow people off
when they're talking to you.
話[はなし]:talk/speech|discussions, 話[わ]:counter for stories, episodes of TV series, etc., あっさり:easily/readily|lightly (seasoned food, applied make-up, etc.), 無視[むし]:disregarding/ignoring
（ハチマキ）おい
人の話をあっさり無視すんな
新入社員[しんにゅうしゃいん]:new employee/freshman employee/new hire
あっ し… 新入社員の
タナベと言います
M-My name is Tanabe!
I'm a new employee.
You are?
（ハチマキ）お前が？
人事[じんじ]:personnel affairs/human affairs/human resources, 人事[ひとごと, たにんごと]:other people's affairs/somebody else's problem
そういや 人事のやつ
１人 来るとか言ってたな
Come to think of it, Human Resources said
something about us getting somebody new...
うわあ:Wow!/Holy smokes!/Aaargh!
（タナベ）うわあ！
逃げる[にげる]:to escape/to run away, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
（ハチマキ）お前な 逃げるなんて
先輩を何だと思ってるんだ？
Note: Senpai is term of respect given to an elder, mentor or a more senior person.
Hey, I'm your senpai. What's the big idea,
running away from your Senpai?
ちゃんと:diligently/seriously|perfectly, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
（タナベ）でも
下 ちゃんと はいてください
B-But, well, put something on
down there!
（ハチマキ）下？ はいてるだろ
Down where?
I am wearing something.
But they're diapers!
おむつ:diaper/nappy/napkin
（タナベ）おむつじゃないですか
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 飛行士[ひこうし]:pilot
（ハチマキ）
宇宙飛行士ってのはなあ―
All astronauts wear diapers!
You should know that!
おむつ:diaper/nappy/napkin
みんな おむつ はくんだよ
知ってんだろうが！
くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
（タナベ）来ないで！ ください
Stay away!
Please.
Say what?! Who do you
think you are, rookie?!
新入り[しんいり]:newcomer/initiate/rookie
（ハチマキ）
何だと！ 新入りのくせに
だって…
But...
When you're out in the field,
this is what you wear!
現場[げんば, げんじょう]:actual spot/scene|shop floor, 当たり前[あたりまえ]:natural/reasonable|usual
（ハチマキ）現場じゃ
これが当たり前なんだよ！
学生[がくせい]:student (esp. a university student), 学生[がくしょう, がくそう]:Heian-period student of government administration|Buddhist scholar|learning, 気分[きぶん]:feeling/mood, たたく[たたく]:to strike|to play drums|to abuse||, 直す[なおす]:to cure|to fix|to do over again (after -masu base of verb)||
（ハチマキ）学生気分を
たたき直してやるから―
I'm gonna knock some real-world
sense into you, so get ready!
覚悟[かくご]:resolution/resignation/readiness, やがる:verb suffix indicating hatred and contempt, or disdain for another's action
覚悟しやがれ！
But couldn't this be thought of
as sexual harassment?
セクハラ:sexual harassment
でも こういうのって
セクハラじゃないんですか？
（課長）あっ！？
（ラビィ）えっ！？
Sexual harassment?!
セクハラ:sexual harassment
（課長）セクハラ？
You aren't going to sue, are you?
まさか:by no means/never!|something unexpected, 訴える[うったえる]:to raise|to appeal to (reason, emotions, etc.)|to complain||
（ラビィ）
君 まさか 訴えたりしないよね？
Chief, call Legal Affairs at once!
課長[かちょう]:section manager/section chief, 法務[ほうむ]:judicial affairs|clerical duty (in a temple), 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 連絡[れんらく]:to contact|contacting|connection|
課長 今すぐ 法務課へ連絡を
公にする[おおやけにする]:to make public
（課長）公にしないでよ～
（ユーリ）あっ…
Please, don't go public
with this!
乗る[のる]:to get on (train, plane, bus, ship, etc.)|to get on (e.g. a footstool)|to reach||, いやいや:no!/no no!/no, not at all, いやいや:unwillingly/grudgingly|shaking head in refusal (to children)
わっ いや 何か乗った！
何か乗った いやいや
Something's on me!
Get it off!
（フィー）何すんだよ！
Hey, what's the big idea?!
Hey! For the last time,
no cigarettes!
タバコ:tobacco/cigarette/cigaret, 駄目[だめ, ダメ]:no good|hopeless|cannot|
ちょっと！ タバコは駄目だって
うわあ:Wow!/Holy smokes!/Aaargh!
うわあ！
（課長たち）ああっ
（タナベ）うわっ… うあっ
（ユーリ）ああ ちょっと
おい ああ… 待っておくれ
Hey, come back!
Come back!
うわあ:Wow!/Holy smokes!/Aaargh!
（ハチマキ）あ？ うわ うわあ！
あああ:Aah!/Ooh!/Oh No!
（タナベ）
え？ あっ あっ ああああーっ！
Over here, miss,
over here.
（ラビィ）
あー 君 君 こっちこっち
フンッ
こちら:this way (direction close to the speaker or towards the speaker)/this direction|here (place close to the speaker or where the speaker is), デブリ:debris, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 課長[かちょう]:section manager/section chief, 補佐[ほさ]:aid/help/assistance
（ラビィ）えー
こちらがデブリ課 課長補佐―
This is Philippe Myers, assistant section
manager for Debris Section.
フィリップ:fillip/Philip, 一番[いちばん]:number one|best|game||, 一番[ひとつがい]:pair/couple/brace, 偉い[えらい]:great/excellent|awful, 方[かた]:direction|person|method of||, 方[ほう]:direction|side (of an argument, etc.)|type||
フィリップ･マイヤーズ
つまり うちで 一番偉いお方
In other words,
he's the top dog here.
I look forward to working
with you, sir.
よろしく:well/properly|best regards, 願う[ねがう]:to desire|to beg|to have something done for oneself
（タナベ）よろしく お願いします
よろしく:well/properly|best regards
はい よろしくね
Of course.
Same here.
係[かかり]:charge/duty|connection, 係[がかり]:charge/duty/person in charge, 長[たけ, たき]:height|length (esp. of clothing)|all (one has)|, 長[ちょう]:head|merit|superiority|, 補佐[ほさ]:aid/help/assistance
そして 私が係長… 補佐
アルヴィンド･ラビィ
And I'm the supervisor (assistant),
Arvind Lavie.
ナンバー:number
ここのナンバー２
I'm number two
around here!
よろしく:well/properly|best regards, 願う[ねがう]:to desire|to beg|to have something done for oneself
よろしく お願いします
It's a pleasure
to meet you!
Oh, this?
アハハ:a-ha-ha (laughing loudly), 今度[こんど]:this time|next time|recently, 総務[そうむ]:general affairs/general business/manager, 会[え]:gathering (esp. Buddhist, festive, etc.), 会[かい]:meeting/assembly|association
アハハ これ？
今度 総務の歓送迎会があってさ
This is for the sendoff and welcoming
party at General Affairs later.
Really?
はあ
会社[かいしゃ]:company/corporation|workplace
そんなことより
君も もう会社人なんだから―
The important thing is that you're a company girl now, so make sure you remember the pecking order, okay?
挨拶[あいさつ]:greeting|polite set phrase used to express apology, sympathy, congratulations, etc.|speech (congratulatory or appreciative)||, 順番[じゅんばん]:turn (in line)/order of things/sequential order, 守る[まもる]:to protect/to guard|to keep (i.e. a promise)
挨拶の順番は 守るように
（タナベ）はい？
Excuse me?
Greet the most important
person first.
偉い[えらい]:great/excellent|awful, 順番[じゅんばん]:turn (in line)/order of things/sequential order
偉い人から順番
ああ はい
R-Right.
Still, I'm glad you're here. It's been
three years since our last newcomer.
新人[しんじん]:new face/newcomer|modern humans (from Cro-Magnon man onwards)
（課長）でも よく来てくれたね
３年ぶりの新人だよ
え？
デブリ:debris, 回収[かいしゅう]:collection/recovery/withdrawal, 正直[しょうじき]:honesty/integrity|honestly, お金[おかね]:money
デブリの回収って
正直 お金にならないんだよね
To be honest, there's no money
to be made in collecting debris.
課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 毎年[まいとし, まいねん]:every year/yearly/annually, 成績[せいせき]:results/record/grades, 最下位[さいかい]:lowest rank/bottom|least significant (bit)
だから うちの課は
毎年 成績最下位でさ
So our section's performance
rates at the bottom each year.
But it's like that at the debris sections
of every other company, Chief!
課長[かちょう]:section manager/section chief, 会社[かいしゃ]:company/corporation|workplace, デブリ:debris, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book)
（ラビィ）課長 どこの会社でも
デブリ課は そんなものですって
We're the bottom
of the barrel.
ぶっちぎり:establishing a large lead over one's competitors/breaking away (from the field)
でも うちは ぶっちぎりだよ
You see this room?
It used to be a cargo bay.
たって:strongly hoping or requesting (of something that is difficult to be brought to fruition), たって:even if/even though|however, 元[もと]:origin|base|cause||, 元[げん]:unknown (e.g. in an equation)|element (of a set)|yuan (monetary unit of China)|, 倉庫[そうこ]:storehouse/warehouse/godown
ここにしたって
元は ただの倉庫だしさ
Anyway, don't expect
to move up in the world.
出世[しゅっせ]:success in life/getting ahead/successful career, 期待[きたい]:expectation/anticipation/hope
まっ 出世とかは期待するな
仕事[しごと]:work/job|work, きつい:intense/severe|determined, 危険[きけん]:danger/peril|risk, 予算[よさん]:estimate/budget, しょぼい:shabby/dull|gloomy
仕事は きついし危険だし
予算は しょぼい
The work's hard, it's dangerous, our budget
is a joke, and then there's the diapers...
おむつ:diaper/nappy/napkin
その上 おむつだ
Hachi!
What if she quits?!
新人[しんじん]:new face/newcomer|modern humans (from Cro-Magnon man onwards), 辞める[やめる]:to resign/to retire/to quit
（ラビィ）
ハチ！ 新人が辞めたら…
くらい:dark/gloomy|dark (in colour), くらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that, 辞める[やめる]:to resign/to retire/to quit, 最初[さいしょ]:beginning/outset/first, 要る[いる]:to need/to want
これくらいで辞めるんなら
最初っから要らねえよ
If that's enough to make her quit,
we're better off without her.
んっ…
Even if there's no money in it,
it's a job that needs to be done.
お金[おかね]:money
（フィー）お金にならなくてもね
いける:to arrange (flowers)/to plant|living, いける:to be good (at)/to go well|to look (taste, etc.) good, 仕事[しごと]:work/job|work
誰かが
やんなきゃいけない仕事なのよ
訓練[くんれん]:training/drill/practice, 校[こう]:school|proof (of a book, document, etc.)/counter for proofs, 出[で]:coming out|attending (work)|start||, 出[しゅつ]:coming out/emerging|being born into (a certain family)
へえ 訓練校出じゃないんだ
Oh, you're not out of the
astronaut academy, huh?
（タナベ）あの…
Um...
Fee Carmichael. I captain
the debris recovery ship Toy Box.
フィー:phi
フィー･カーマイケル
デブリ:debris, 回収[かいしゅう]:collection/recovery/withdrawal, 船[ふね]:ship|tank|counter for boat-shaped containers (e.g. of sashimi), 船長[せんちょう, ふなおさ]:ship's captain|length of a ship|boatman
デブリ回収船
ToyBox(トイボックス)の船長やってる
Yuri!
ユーリ
This is my first mate,
Yuri Mihairokoh.
副[ふく]:assistant|duplicate|adverb, 船長[せんちょう, ふなおさ]:ship's captain|length of a ship|boatman
副船長のユーリ･ミハイロコフ
わざわざ:expressly/specially/doing something especially rather than incidentally
（タナベ）あっ どうも わざわざ
Pleased to meet you.
That's Edelgard Rivera.
She's a temp staffer.
派遣社員[はけんしゃいん]:temporary employee (esp. from an agency)/temporary worker/agency temp
（フィー）彼女は派遣社員の
エーデルガルド･リヴェラ
She takes care of
the office work for us.
事務[じむ]:business/office work/administration, 全般[ぜんぱん]:(the) whole/universal/wholly
事務全般をやってくれてる
派遣[はけん]:dispatch/despatch|temporary employee (esp. from an agency)
派遣ですか
She's a temp?
上司[じょうし]:superior authorities/boss, 派遣[はけん]:dispatch/despatch|temporary employee (esp. from an agency)
上司も
派遣してくれるといいのにねえ
I wish they'd send us
temp superiors like her, too...
フィー:phi, 上司[じょうし]:superior authorities/boss, 批判[ひはん]:criticism/judgement/judgment
フィー君 上司批判は…
Fee! Criticism of
your superiors... -
ああん:opening (one's mouth) wide/saying "aah"|crying loudly
（フィー）ああん？
ほどほど:moderate
ほどほどにねえ フゥ…
- should be used
in moderation.
クフフフ…
（フィー）んで―
And last but not least,
that's Hoshino Hachirota.
残る[のこる]:to remain/to be left
残ったあいつが星野(ほしの)八郎太(はちろうた)
ハチマキ:headband, 通る[とおる]:to go by|to run (between)|to go indoors||
“ハチマキ”で通ってる
We call him Hachimaki.
Like a hachimaki
headband?
ハチマキ:headband
（タナベ）ハチマキ？
まんま:as it is/as one likes|condition, まんま:cooked rice
まんまですね
It fits.
Get off my case! I didn't
give myself the nickname!
付ける[つける]:to attach|to furnish (a house with)|to wear||, あだ名[あだな, こんめい]:nickname
（ハチマキ）うるせえなあ
俺が付けたあだ名じゃねえよ！
Come on, play nice.
仲良く[なかよく]:on good terms with/on cordial terms with|to make friends with, なさる:to do
ほら 仲良くしなさい
I'm teaming you up with her, after all.
コンビ:combination/pair/duo, 組む[くむ]:to cross (legs or arms)|to put together|to braid||, もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something
あんたには
彼女とコンビを組んでもらうから
ええっ！？
（ハチマキ）なんでだよ！
Why?!
She works EVA, too.
資材[しざい]:(raw) material, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 服[ふく]:clothes (esp. Western clothes)|counter for doses of medicine, gulps of tea, drags of a cigarette, etc., 服[ぶく]:mourning clothes|mourning/period of mourning, 合わせ[あわせ]:joint together/opposite/facing
（フィー）こいつも ＥＶＡでね
資材課で服合わせやっといて
Go over to Materials Section and
get her fitted for a spacesuit, okay?
（ラビィ）ＥＶＡって 何だっけ？
What's "EVA"
stand for again?
I thought I was an extravehicular
activity worker...
船外[せんがい]:outboard/extra-vehicular, 活動[かつどう]:action/activity|movie (esp. during the silent movie period), 員[いん]:member
（タナベ）私 船外活動員じゃ…
同じ[おなじ, おんなじ]:same/identical|(usu. part of a 'nara' conditional) anyway, 意味[いみ]:meaning/significance
（ハチマキ）同じ意味だ！
It means
the same thing!
O-Oh, of course.
よろしく:well/properly|best regards, 願う[ねがう]:to desire|to beg|to have something done for oneself
あいっ は… はい そうでした
よろしく お願いします
I look forward to working with you.
Geez, I can't believe these
general hires...
一般[いっぱん]:general/universal|ordinary, 入社[にゅうしゃ]:joining a company/getting a job with a company/entering a company
（ハチマキ）たく 一般入社は
わあ！
社員[しゃいん]:company employee|company stockholders (esp. in legal contexts)/members of a corporation
（社員１）
はい ＯＫ もういいわよ
Okay, all done.
You can go now.
（タナベ）えっ あの まだ…
But I still haven't...
社員[しゃいん]:company employee|company stockholders (esp. in legal contexts)/members of a corporation, 宇宙服[うちゅうふく]:space suit, 丸ごと[まるごと]:in its entirety/whole/wholly, オーダー:order, 大[おお]:big/large, 大[だい]:the large part of|big|approximate size||, 赤字[あかじ]:deficit|red text|corrections (by a teacher or proofreader) written in red
（社員１）宇宙服を
丸ごとオーダーしてたら大赤字だわ
If we custom-made every spacesuit,
we'd run ourselves into the red.
Customizing parts of them
is good enough.
部分[ぶぶん]:portion/section/part, オーダー:order, 十分[じっぷん, じゅっぷん]:10 minutes, 十分[じゅうぶん]:plenty|division into ten|perfectly
部分オーダーしておけば十分なの
（タナベ）ほう…
We have one-size-fits-all spacesuits
in the next room, so go put one on.
社員[しゃいん]:company employee|company stockholders (esp. in legal contexts)/members of a corporation, 次[つぎ]:next/following|stage, 次[じ]:next|hypo- (i.e. containing an element with low valence)|order, 部屋[へや]:room|apartment|stable, 出来合い[できあい]:ready-made/common-law (wife), 宇宙服[うちゅうふく]:space suit
（社員１）次の部屋に
出来合いの宇宙服あるから
はい
Yes, ma'am!
Hey, wait!
社員[しゃいん]:company employee|company stockholders (esp. in legal contexts)/members of a corporation
（社員１）あっ ちょっと
（タナベ）はい？
Ma'am?
We can't have you leaving your
oversized garbage lying around.
社員[しゃいん]:company employee|company stockholders (esp. in legal contexts)/members of a corporation, 粗大ゴミ[そだいごみ, そだいゴミ]:oversize garbage/bulky rubbish|husband, 置く[おく]:to put|to leave (behind)|to establish (an organization, a facility, a position, etc.)||, 困る[こまる]:to be troubled/to be worried/to be bothered
（社員１）粗大ゴミ
置いていかれると困るんだけど
引き取る[ひきとる]:to take over|to take charge of|to retire to a private place, いただく:to receive/to get|to eat
はい 引き取らせていただきます
Yes, ma'am.
I'll take it off your hands.
（タナベ）どうですか？
How does it look?
社員[しゃいん]:company employee|company stockholders (esp. in legal contexts)/members of a corporation, ナイス:nice, バディ:buddy
（社員２）いいねえ ナイスバディ
Just great!
Nice body!
次[つぎ]:next/following|stage, 次[じ]:next|hypo- (i.e. containing an element with low valence)|order, フェイス:face, パネル:panel, テスト:test
じゃあ 次は
フェイスパネルのテストだ
Okay, we'll run face panel tests next.
You know how to do that, right?
知ってるよね？
研修[けんしゅう]:training (esp. in-service)/induction course, 習う[ならう]:to take lessons in/to be taught/to learn (from a teacher)
（タナベ）
はい 研修で習いましたから
Yes, sir. I learned that
during our workshops.
社員[しゃいん]:company employee|company stockholders (esp. in legal contexts)/members of a corporation, よーし:alright/all right/right on, 軸[じく]:axis|center|stalk|, 合わせ[あわせ]:joint together/opposite/facing
（社員２）
よーし じゃあ 軸合わせからだ
All right, let's start with axis alignment.
Try setting your artificial horizon to Earth.
仮想[かそう]:imagination/supposition/virtual, 水平線[すいへいせん]:horizon (related to sea or lakes), 地球[ちきゅう]:the earth/the globe, 合わせる[あわせる]:to match (rhythm, speed, etc.)|to join together|to face||
仮想水平線を
地球に合わせてみて
（タナベ）はい
Yes, sir!
管制[かんせい]:control, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book)
たく 管制課のせいで
Man, this is all
Control Section's fault...
ハチマキ:headband
（キース）おう ハチマキ
（ハチマキ）よう
Hey, Hachimaki.
Hey.
What are you guys gonna do about
that debris that everybody's talking about?
例[れい]:custom|said|instance|, 例[ためし]:precedent/example, デブリ:debris
お前んとこ
例のデブリ どうすんだ？
Beats me. Sounds like the top brass
are still fighting it out.
みたい:-like/sort of/similar to
さあね 上も モメてるみたいだし
Okay, time for your next stop,
diaper girl!
次[つぎ]:next/following|stage, 次[じ]:next|hypo- (i.e. containing an element with low valence)|order, おむつ:diaper/nappy/napkin
よし 次 行くぞ おむつ女
Come on, Senpai,
don't shout it out!
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 大声[おおごえ, たいせい]:loud voice
ちょっと先輩 そんな大声で
This is the real thing...
本物[ほんもの]:genuine article/real thing/real deal
（タナベ）本物なんだよね
うっ
（ハチマキ）まっ こんなもんか
Well, that oughta
do it.
Senpai, that's one more
than what's on our list.
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, リスト:list
先輩 これ
リストより １つ多いんですけど
困る[こまる]:to be troubled/to be worried/to be bothered
（ハチマキ）
多い分には困らないだろ？
Having an extra
won't kill us, right?
We can't! We have
to do this by the book!
駄目[だめ, ダメ]:no good|hopeless|cannot|, きちんと:properly/accurately|neatly
駄目です
こういうのは きちんとしないと
Of all the stupid...
たくよお ああ…
隣[となり]:neighbor (neighbour)/next to (esp. living next door to), 棚[たな]:shelf/shelves|trellis
隣の棚です！
It's on the next shelf over!
Please return it to where you got it!
ちゃんと:diligently/seriously|perfectly, 元[もと]:origin|base|cause||, 元[げん]:unknown (e.g. in an equation)|element (of a set)|yuan (monetary unit of China)|, 戻す[もどす]:to put back|to vomit|to recover (of a market price), くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
ちゃんと
元のところに戻してくださいよ
真面目[しんめんもく, しんめんぼく]:one's true character/one's true self|seriousness, 真面目[まじめ]:diligent/serious/honest, すぎる:to pass through/to pass by|to pass (i.e. of time)
お前 真面目すぎるぞ
You're taking things
too seriously.
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 不真面目[ふまじめ]:unsteadiness/lack of sincerity
（タナベ）
先輩が 不真面目なんですよ
You don't take them
seriously enough!
Yeah, yeah, yeah...
あー はいはい
頑張る[がんばる]:to persevere|to insist that|to remain in a place
じゃ これからは
俺の分も頑張ってくれよ
You work real hard and be serious
enough for the both of us, okay?
Oh, right. Maybe I'll put in
some food, too...
飯[めし]:cooked rice|meal|one's livelihood, 飯[まんま, まま]:cooked rice, ついで:next/secondly/subsequently, ついで:opportunity/occasion, 入れる[いれる]:to put in|to admit|to accept||
あっ 飯もついでに入れとこーっと
Is everyone else
like this?
他[ほか]:other (place, thing, person)|outside|nothing except|, 他[た]:other (esp. people and abstract matters)
他の人もそうなんですか？
（ハチマキ）あ？
Huh?
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 飛行士[ひこうし]:pilot
（タナベ）宇宙飛行士って―
I always thought that astronauts
would be more amazing.
もっと:(some) more/even more/longer, すごい:terrible/dreadful|amazing (e.g. of strength)
もっと
すごい人たちだと思ってました
常[とこ]:constant/unchanging/eternal, 常[ただ, タダ]:ordinary|free of charge|unaffected||, 節制[せっせい]:moderation/self-restraint/temperance, 勇敢[ゆうかん]:brave/heroic/gallant, 紳士[しんし]:gentleman
常に節制して 勇敢で 紳士で
That they'd always be restrained,
and brave, and earnest...
話す[はなす]:to talk|to tell|to speak (a language)
（ハチマキ）
お前なあ いつの話してんだよ
In this day and age?
What are you talking about?
This is 2075, you know. Things aren't like
when man first set foot on the moon.
2075年だぞ
人類[じんるい]:mankind/humanity, 初めて[はじめて]:for the first time|only after ... is it .../only when ... do you ..., 立つ[たつ]:to stand|to find oneself (e.g. in a difficult position)|to depart (on a plane, train, etc.)
人類が初めて
月に立ったころとは違うんだ
大体[だいたい]:outline|general|in the first place, てめえ:you (used by young males)|oneself, 入社[にゅうしゃ]:joining a company/getting a job with a company/entering a company, 時点[じてん]:point in time/occasion
大体 てめえが
入社できてる時点で違うだろ
Hell, they changed the instant
you managed to join the company.
そりゃ:very/extremely|that is
（タナベ）
まあ そりゃ そうですけど
Well, you have a point...
But it's kinda different from...
でも 何か思ってたのと…
Okay, we'll need
these, too.
（ハチマキ）はい これも
（タナベ）えっ… 何ですか？ これ
What's that?
エロ本[エロほん]:erotic book
（ハチマキ）
お前 エロ本 見たことないのか？
What, you've never seen
a porno mag before?
そういうことじゃありません
That's not what I mean! Why would
we need something like that?!
物[もの, もん]:thing|one's things|things||, 物[ぶつ, ブツ]:stock/products|stolen goods, 要る[いる]:to need/to want
どうして
こんな物が要るんですか？
We need it. Depending on the job, men and
women can be together for days at a time.
要る[いる]:to need/to want
要るんだよ
仕事[しごと]:work/job|work, 何日[なんにち]:what day|how many days, 一緒[いっしょ]:together|at the same time|same
仕事によっては
男と女が何日も一緒にいるんだぞ
If we don't take matters into our own hands,
it could lead to trouble, right?
気分[きぶん]:feeling/mood, 逃がす[にがす]:to set free/to let go|to miss (e.g. a chance), ヤバい:dangerous|awful|terrific
そういう気分を どっかに
逃がさないと ヤバいだろうが
ほれ お前の分
Here. This one's
for you.
ううっ
（ハチマキ）うわあああーっ！
What a disaster...
最悪[さいあく]:the worst|in the worst case
（タナベ）もう最悪
リュシーたちと違ってさ―
Unlike you guys, I'm stuck with
cigarettes, animals, magic tricks,
タバコ:tobacco/cigarette/cigaret, 動物[どうぶつ]:animal, マジック:magic, ショー:show
こっちは タバコと動物と
マジックショーと―
...and a guy in diapers with a knack
for sexual harassment.
セクハラ:sexual harassment, おむつ:diaper/nappy/napkin
セクハラのおむつ男なんだよ？
なるほど:I see/That's right!/Indeed, 半[はん]:half|half-past|odd number|, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book)
（シャポウ）なるほど 半課だね
I'm not surprised.
That's Half Section for you.
Half Section?
半[はん]:half|half-past|odd number|, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book)
（タナベ）半課？
管制[かんせい]:control, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book)
そういや
管制課の人も言ってたけど…
Now that you mention it, someone
in Control Section called them...
デブリ:debris, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 計画[けいかく]:plan/project/schedule, 滞る[とどこおる]:to stagnate/to be delayed|to be overdue (of a payment)
（ヴァンリ）うちのデブリ課ってさ
何か計画が滞ってて―
They say that our Debris Section
plan got held up somehow,
予定[よてい]:plans/arrangement/schedule, 半分[はんぶん]:half, 半分[はんぷん]:half minute
予定の半分しか
人がいないんだって
...so they only have half the personnel
they were supposed to.
They're a section with only half
a staff, so "Half Section."
半分[はんぶん]:half, 半分[はんぷん]:half minute, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), 半[はん]:half|half-past|odd number|
だから
半分しかいない課で“半課”
確か[たしか]:sure|reliable|If I'm not mistaken
それと確か―
And they're supposed to be
half-trained, half-assed,
半端[はんぱ]:remnant|fraction|halfway|, 反抗的[はんこうてき]:rebellious/defiant, 反省[はんせい]:reflection/reconsideration|regret, 犯罪[はんざい]:crime/offence/offense
半人前 半端者 反抗的
反省しない 犯罪…
...half-cocked, half-hearted,
half-crazy, and...
I'm gonna
hang in there!
頑張る[がんばる]:to persevere|to insist that|to remain in a place
私 頑張るから！
あっ そう？
Oh, really?
They're not gonna beat me!
Not Half Section, and not even diaper man!
半[はん]:half|half-past|odd number|, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book), おむつ:diaper/nappy/napkin, 負ける[まける]:to lose|to succumb|to be inferior to||
（タナベ）半課だろうが
おむつ男だろうが 負けないから！
頑張る[がんばる]:to persevere|to insist that|to remain in a place
あっ 頑張ってね
W-Well, give it
your best shot.
任せる[まかせる]:to entrust (e.g. a task) to another|to passively leave to someone else's facilities|to leave to take its natural course||
うん 任せて！
Yeah, let me
at 'em!
（タナベ）いやぁ！
自分でやりますって 自分で
I'll do it myself,
I'll do it myself!
Pipe down.
うるさい:noisy/loud|annoying
（ハチマキ）うるさい
もしかし:perhaps/maybe/by some chance, さっき:some time ago/just now, さっき:thirst for blood/bloodlust/determination to kill, 恨む[うらむ]:to resent/to curse|to regret
もしかして
さっきのこと恨んでます？
Don't tell me you're still mad
about earlier!
当たり前[あたりまえ]:natural/reasonable|usual, 思いっ切り[おもいきり, おもいっきり]:with all one's strength/with all one's heart/resignation, やがる:verb suffix indicating hatred and contempt, or disdain for another's action
当たり前だろ！
思いっ切り やりやがって
Of course I am!
You hit me as hard as you could!
ハチマキ:headband, 執行[しっこう, しゅぎょう]:execution/carrying out|lead monk performing various tasks in a temple, 手続き[てつづき]:procedure/(legal) process/formalities, 終わる[おわる]:to finish/to end/to close
ハチマキ
執行手続き 終わったから
Hachimaki, all our departure
paperwork is finished.
おう
Right.
Stop horsing around, Tanabe.
Hurry it up.
遊ぶ[あそぶ, あすぶ]:to play|to mess about (with alcohol, gambling, philandery, etc.)|to be idle||, 遊ぶ[すさぶ]:to grow wild/to rage|to do something one enjoys, 早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|
タナベも遊んでないで早くしな
だってよ
You heard her.
We're really going out
into space?
ほんと:truth/reality|proper, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space
ほんとに宇宙に出るんですか？
現場[げんば, げんじょう]:actual spot/scene|shop floor, 仕事[しごと]:work/job|work
（フィー）現場に行かなきゃ
仕事になんないでしょ
We can't do our job if we don't
go out into the field, right?
ばっかり:only/merely|approximately, 船[ふね]:ship|tank|counter for boat-shaped containers (e.g. of sashimi)
（タナベ）でも 私
今日 来たばっかりで船のことも…
But I just got here today!
I don't know anything about ships!
（ユーリ）だったら 大丈夫ですよ
In that case, you'll be fine. This ship
has been flying for over 30 years.
船[ふね]:ship|tank|counter for boat-shaped containers (e.g. of sashimi), 以上[いじょう]:not less than|beyond ... (e.g. one's means)|above-mentioned||, 飛ぶ[とぶ]:to fly/to soar|to jump
この船は もう
30年以上も飛んでいるんですから
古い[ふるい]:old (not person)/aged/ancient
（タナベ）ええっ！？
そんなに古いんですか？
What?! The DS-12
is that old?!
この DS-12って
Toy Box.
（ハチマキ）ToyBox
（タナベ）え？
No self-respecting sailor
calls his ship by its number!
船乗り[ふなのり]:getting on board|sailor/seaman, 型番[かたばん]:model number/pattern number, 呼ぶ[よぶ]:to call out (to)|to summon (a doctor, etc.)|to invite||
（ハチマキ）
船乗りなら 型番で呼ぶな
うわあ:Wow!/Holy smokes!/Aaargh!, 助ける[たすける]:to save|to help|to aid|
（タナベ）うわあ！ 誰か助けてー
Somebody help me!
DS-12, this is ISPV-7.
Comm system multi-channel check.
こちら:this way (direction close to the speaker or towards the speaker)/this direction|here (place close to the speaker or where the speaker is)
（クレア）DS-12 こちらISPV-７
通信[つうしん]:correspondence/communication/transmission, 系統[けいとう]:system|lineage|group (e.g. of colors) (colours)||, マルチ:multi-, チャンネル:channel, チェック:check/plaid/checkered
通信系統
マルチチャンネルチェック
コピー:copy/photocopy
ユー コピー？
You copy?
I copy.
コピー:copy/photocopy
アイ コピー
DS-12, this is ISPV-7.
This is an abort indicator test.
こちら:this way (direction close to the speaker or towards the speaker)/this direction|here (place close to the speaker or where the speaker is)
（クレア）DS-12 こちらISPV-７
アボート:abort, 表示[ひょうじ]:indication|display|representation, テスト:test, コピー:copy/photocopy
アボート表示のテストです
（フィー）アイ コピー
I copy. Check nominal.
- I knew it, they're different
when they're on the job...
やっぱり:too/also|still, 仕事[しごと]:work/job|work
（タナベ）
やっぱり 仕事になると違うんだ
Hey, rookie! Go get a barf bag
and stand by!
新入り[しんいり]:newcomer/initiate/rookie, 袋[ふくろ]:bag|skin of an orange (and other like fruits)|dead end|, 袋[たい]:counter for things inside a bag, 持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||, 待機[たいき]:alert/standby/await an opportunity
（ハチマキ）新入り
ゲロ袋 持って 待機しとけ
酔い止め[よいどめ]:anti-travel sickness (medicine), 飲む[のむ]:to drink|to smoke (tobacco)|to engulf||
（タナベ）
酔い止めなら飲んでますよ
I'm already taking
motion sickness medicine!
Seven, this is DS-12.
Power source switchover complete.
セブン:seven, こちら:this way (direction close to the speaker or towards the speaker)/this direction|here (place close to the speaker or where the speaker is), 電源[でんげん]:source of electricity/electrical power|power (button on TV, etc.), 切り替える[きりかえる]:to change/to exchange/to convert, 完了[かんりょう]:completion/conclusion|perfect (tense, form, aspect), 完了[ワンラ]:end/completion
（フィー）セブンへ
こちらDS-12 電源切り替え完了
アビオニクス:avionics, 各[かく]:each/every/all, 各[おのおの]:each|you (plural), 電気[でんき]:electricity|(electric) light, 系統[けいとう]:system|lineage|group (e.g. of colors) (colours)||, 正常[せいじょう]:normalcy/normality/normal
アビオニクス 各電気系統正常
Avionics and all electrical systems are nominal.
IMU orientation determination...
定位[ていい]:position/orientation, 設定[せってい]:establishment/creation|options setting
ＩＭＵの定位設定…
安心[あんしん]:relief/peace of mind, 安心[あんじん]:obtaining peace of mind through faith or ascetic practice, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
（ドルフ）はい ご安心ください
Please rest assured, sir. We will dispose
of the plate as waste debris.
プレート:plate (often as in "tectonic plate"), 不要[ふよう]:unnecessary/unneeded, デブリ:debris, 処理[しょり]:processing/dealing with/treatment
プレートは
不要デブリとして処理します
Yes, sir.
はい
Main umbilical,
separate.
メイン:main/principal part, セパレート:separate
（フィー）
メイン アンビリカル セパレート
Separation complete.
You copy?
セパレート:separate, コンプリート:complete, コピー:copy/photocopy
（クレア）セパレート
コンプリート ユー コピー？
コピー:copy/photocopy, フリー:free (of restraint, controls, etc.)
（フィー）
アイ コピー テイキング フリー
I copy.
Taking free.
こちら:this way (direction close to the speaker or towards the speaker)/this direction|here (place close to the speaker or where the speaker is), セブン:seven
DS-12 こちらセブン
DS-12, this is Seven.
Establishing datalink via Navstar.
ナブスター:Navstar, 経由[けいゆ, けいゆう]:through/by way of|to go via, データリンク:datalink, 接続[せつぞく]:connection|changing trains|conjunction
ナブスター経由の
データリンク 接続します
接続[せつぞく]:connection|changing trains|conjunction, 確認[かくにん]:confirmation/verification/validation
（フィー）接続確認
Datalink confirmed.
軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, 変更[へんこう]:change/modification/alteration, 操作[そうさ]:operation/management|manipulating to one's benefit
ＭＥによる船位軌道への
軌道名変更操作のため…
We will be making orbital plane change
using ME to reach transfer orbit...
うわあ:Wow!/Holy smokes!/Aaargh!
（タナベ）うわあ！
すっげえ:incredible/unbelievable
どうだ？ すっげえだろ
What do you think?
Cool, huh?
It sure is! It's way prettier than
looking at it on a shuttle!
シャトル:shuttlecock, きれい:pretty/lovely|clean
はい
シャトルから見るよりきれいです
シャトル:shuttlecock, きれい:pretty/lovely|clean
はい
シャトルから見るよりきれいです
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
うっ せ… 先輩 これ
S-Senpai, this, uh...
What is it?
Oh, that broke off this time?
今度[こんど]:this time|next time|recently
何だ？ 今度はこっちか
THIS time?!
今度[こんど]:this time|next time|recently
今度！？
船[ふね]:ship|tank|counter for boat-shaped containers (e.g. of sashimi), ボロい:profitable|worn-out/crumbling
（ハチマキ）
この船 ボロいからなあ
Well, this ship is a heap,
after all.
Are you kidding me?
（タナベ）そんな… そんなあ！
Are you kidding me?!
マズい:unappetising|unskillful|ugly|
そんなのマズくない？
Wouldn't that get us
into trouble?
象[しょう]:phenomenon, 象[ぞう, ゾウ]:elephant (Elephantidae spp.), 社[やしろ]:shrine (usually Shinto), 社[しゃ]:company|regional Chinese god of the earth (or a village built in its honour)|counter for companies, shrines, etc., マーク:mark/symbol/insignia
象はベガ社のマークだしさ
Vega Corporation uses an elephant
in their logo, right?
So why not make one using our own logo?
To show our love for our company.
我が社[わがしゃ]:our company/my company, 愛社[あいしゃ]:devotion to one's company, 精神[せいしん]:mind/soul/heart
だったら
我が社のにしたら？ 愛社精神
Brilliant, Chief!
I'll take that idea and run with it!
さすが:as one would expect|still/all the same, さすが:dagger, 課長[かちょう]:section manager/section chief, アイデア:idea, 頂き[いただき]:crown (of head)|easy win for one|something received
（ラビィ）さすが課長
そのアイデア 頂きですよ
It's a company banquet, after all.
We have to pay attention to these things.
会社[かいしゃ]:company/corporation|workplace, 宴会[えんかい]:party/banquet/reception
（課長）会社の宴会だからさ
辺[へん]:area|side|circumstances, 辺[へ, べ]:surrounding area|shore (of the sea)|suffix used as a rough indicator of location, direction, time, etc., きっちり:exactly/precisely|closely
その辺は
きっちり やっといたほうが
再生紙[さいせいし]:recycled paper, 作る[つくる]:to make|to prepare (food)|to raise||
じゃあ ノーラ君を
再生紙で作っちゃいましょう
In that case, let's make a Mr. Nora
out of recycled paper!
Great idea!
We're contributing to society!
社会貢献[しゃかいこうけん]:contribution to society
いいね 社会貢献 アハハハハ…
The Debris Duo...
デブリ:debris, コンビ:combination/pair/duo
（エーデル）デブリコンビ
宇宙服[うちゅうふく]:space suit, ユニホーム:uniform
（ハチマキ）宇宙服ってのはなあ
俺たちのユニホームなんだ
For us, spacesuits
are our uniform.
Become so familiar with it that you can
put it on even if you're half asleep.
寝ぼける[ねぼける]:to be still half asleep/to be half awake/to be not yet quite awake, 着る[きる]:to wear (in modern Japanese, from the shoulders down)/to put on|to bear (guilt, etc.), 体[からだ]:body|torso|build||, 体[たい]:body|shape|substance||, 覚え込む[おぼえこむ]:to memorize/to fix in memory/to master
寝ぼけてても着られるように
体に覚え込ませとけ
コピー:copy/photocopy
ユー コピー？
（タナベ）えっ？
You copy?
It means, "Do you get it?"
コピー:copy/photocopy
分かったかってこと
ユー コピー？
ああっ 分かりました
I understand.
コピー:copy/photocopy
あっ いえ アイ コピーです
I mean, I copy.
準備[じゅんび]:preparation/setup/arrangements
（フィー）２人とも 準備はいい？
Are you two ready?
We'll be coming up on the plate soon.
そろそろ:slowly/quietly|soon, プレート:plate (often as in "tectonic plate"), 近く[ちかく]:near|nearly (e.g. "it took nearly one year")|shortly
そろそろ プレートの近くだから
プレート:plate (often as in "tectonic plate")
（タナベ）プレート？
Plate?
Our debris for this job is a memorial plate
that was sent up 20 years ago,
今回[こんかい]:now/this time/lately, デブリ:debris
今回のデブリ―
子供たち[こどもたち]:children, 平和[へいわ]:peace/harmony, 平和[ピンフ, ピンホー]:concealed winning hand consisting of chows, a pair that isn't a value pair, and an open wait, 暮らす[くらす]:to live/to get along|to spend (time)
マナンガの子供たちが
平和に暮らせるようにって―
...asking that the children of Mananga
be allowed to live in peace.
打ち上げる[うちあげる]:to launch|(of waves) to dash|to finish (e.g. a theater run, sumo tournament)|, 打ち上げる[ぶちあげる]:to make a bold speech/to make a bold statement, 記念[きねん]:commemoration/celebration/honoring the memory of something, プレート:plate (often as in "tectonic plate")
20年前に
打ち上げた記念プレートよ
Its orbit intersects that of
an artificial satellite.
人工衛星[じんこうえいせい]:man-made satellite, 軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, 重なる[かさなる]:to be piled up|to come one after another|to overlap (each other), 重なる[おもなる]:main/principal/important
それが 人工衛星の軌道に
重なっちゃったわけ
Your first job is to scrap it
by dropping it towards Earth.
そいつ:he/she|that, 地球[ちきゅう]:the earth/the globe, 向ける[むける]:to turn towards/to point, 廃棄[はいき]:disposal/abandonment|annulment, 初[はつ, うい]:first/new, 初[うぶ]:innocent/naive|birth-, 仕事[しごと]:work/job|work
（ハチマキ）そいつを地球に向けて
廃棄するのが お前の初仕事だ
廃棄[はいき]:disposal/abandonment|annulment, 回収[かいしゅう]:collection/recovery/withdrawal
廃棄って 回収じゃないんですか？
Scrap it? You mean
we're not retrieving it?
Debris that can't be used as raw material
gets dropped and burned.
資源[しげん]:resources, デブリ:debris, 落とす[おとす]:to drop|to clean off (dirt, makeup, paint, etc.)|to lose (a match)||, 燃やす[もやす, もす]:to burn
資源になりそうにないデブリは
落として燃やしちまうんだよ
But it's a plate
that's a message of peace!
平和[へいわ]:peace/harmony, 平和[ピンフ, ピンホー]:concealed winning hand consisting of chows, a pair that isn't a value pair, and an open wait, プレート:plate (often as in "tectonic plate")
（タナベ）でも
平和のためのプレートですよ？
平和[へいわ]:peace/harmony, 平和[ピンフ, ピンホー]:concealed winning hand consisting of chows, a pair that isn't a value pair, and an open wait
（ハチマキ）ケッ！ そんなもんで
平和になんか ならねえっての
As if something like that
could ever create peace...
The desire to create peace and cherish it
is what will bring peace to the world!
作る[つくる]:to make|to prepare (food)|to raise||, 大事[だいじ, おおごと]:important/valuable|safe (Tochigi dialect), 気持ち[きもち]:feeling|preparedness|thanks|
それを作ろう
大事にしようって気持ちが―
世界[せかい]:the world|sphere|renowned|, 平和[へいわ]:peace/harmony, 平和[ピンフ, ピンホー]:concealed winning hand consisting of chows, a pair that isn't a value pair, and an open wait
世界を平和にするんですよ
Maybe a diaper man like you wouldn't
understand that, Senpai.
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, みたい:-like/sort of/similar to, おむつ:diaper/nappy/napkin, しれる:to become known/to come to light|to be known
先輩みたいな おむつ男には
分からないかもしれませんけど
ったく:good grief (expression of exasperation), 青い[あおい]:blue|pale|unripe, 新入り[しんいり]:newcomer/initiate/rookie
（ハチマキ）ったく
何 青いこと言ってんだ 新入り
Geez... Would you listen to that naive crap
you're spouting, rookie?
When it comes to doing what's right,
there's no senpais or rookies!
正しい[ただしい]:right/correct|proper, 新入り[しんいり]:newcomer/initiate/rookie, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
（タナベ）正しいことに
新入りも先輩もありません！
大体[だいたい]:outline|general|in the first place, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
大体 先輩は…
And anyway, you...
Okay, that's enough
of that.
（フィー）はーい そこまで
タナベ
あんたの言うことも分かるけど―
Tanabe, I can understand what
you're saying, but this is our job.
仕事[しごと]:work/job|work
これは仕事なの
プレート:plate (often as in "tectonic plate"), 大事[だいじ, おおごと]:important/valuable|safe (Tochigi dialect), 人工衛星[じんこうえいせい]:man-made satellite
プレートも大事だけど
人工衛星も大事なのよ
That plate may be important,
but so is that satellite.
But we don't have to
scrap it...
廃棄[はいき]:disposal/abandonment|annulment
（タナベ）でも 廃棄しなくても
指示[しじ, しし]:indication/denotation|instructions
（フィー）上からの指示
Orders from
the bosses.
Somebody has to do
the job.
いける:to arrange (flowers)/to plant|living, いける:to be good (at)/to go well|to look (taste, etc.) good, 仕事[しごと]:work/job|work
誰かが
やらなけりゃ いけない仕事なの
Getting rid of debris in orbit
is vital to space development.
軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, デブリ:debris, なくす:to lose something|to get rid of, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 開発[かいはつ, かいほつ]:development/exploitation, つながる:to be tied together/to be connected to|to lead to
軌道上のデブリをなくすことが
宇宙開発につながるのよ
分かるわね
（タナベ）はい
Understand?
Yes, ma'am.
嫌[いや, や]:disagreeable/detestable/unpleasant, 愛[あい]:love/affection|attachment, 愛[まな]:beloved/dear
（タナベ）分かるけど
そんなの嫌だな 愛がない
I understand, but...
It's just not right.
There's no love!
デブリ:debris, 回収[かいしゅう]:collection/recovery/withdrawal, 船[ふね]:ship|tank|counter for boat-shaped containers (e.g. of sashimi), 予定[よてい]:plans/arrangement/schedule, ポイント:point, 到着[とうちゃく]:arrival
（クレア）デブリ回収船 DS-12は
予定ポイントに到着しました
Debris collector ship DS-12
has arrived at target point.
プレート:plate (often as in "tectonic plate"), 連合[れんごう]:union/alliance|RENGO (Japanese Trade Union Confederation), 衛星[えいせい]:satellite, 接触[せっしょく]:touch/contact
プレートと連合の衛星が
接触するまで 58分です
T minus 58 minutes to contact between
the plate and the INTO satellite.
連合[れんごう]:union/alliance|RENGO (Japanese Trade Union Confederation), 随分[ずいぶん]:very/extremely|contemptible, 神経質[しんけいしつ]:nervous/highly strung|fussy
連合は随分 神経質になっているが
INTO is starting
to get pretty jumpy.
廃棄[はいき]:disposal/abandonment|annulment, 指示[しじ, しし]:indication/denotation|instructions, 通達[つうたつ, つうだつ]:notification/official notice|being well versed (in something), 済み[ずみ, すみ]:arranged/taken care of/settled
廃棄指示は 通達済みです
The disposal order
has been sent.
以降[いこう]:on and after/as from/hereafter, 定時[ていじ]:regular time/stated period, 連絡[れんらく]:to contact|contacting|connection|, 各[かく]:each/every/all, 各[おのおの]:each|you (plural), 工程[こうてい]:process/operation/stage of a process, チェック:check/plaid/checkered
以降 定時連絡で
各工程をチェックします
I'll check each stage of the operation during
our regularly scheduled communications.
（ドルフ）分かった
Very well.
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 怖い[こわい]:scary/frightening|(I'm) afraid
（タナベ）あの 先輩
怖いんですけど これ
Um, Senpai?
I'm a little scared...
Like they say, the best time to learn
to swim is when you're drowning.
溺れる[おぼれる]:to drown/to nearly drown|to indulge in, ながら:while/during|while, 覚える[おぼえる]:to memorize|to learn|to feel|, 一番[いちばん]:number one|best|game||, 一番[ひとつがい]:pair/couple/brace
溺れながら覚えるのが
一番なんだって
Don't say that!
I don't wanna drown in space!
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 溺れる[おぼれる]:to drown/to nearly drown|to indulge in, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
（タナベ）
そんなあ 宇宙で溺れるなんて！
大丈夫でしょうか？ 彼女
Do you think she's
going to work out?
研修[けんしゅう]:training (esp. in-service)/induction course
（フィー）
まっ 研修もやってるし―
Well, she's taking workshops,
and we'll be in trouble...
早い[はやい]:fast|early (in the day, etc.)|(too) soon|, 戦力[せんりょく]:war potential/military strength|ability (to compete), もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something
早いとこ
戦力になってもらわないと―
...if we don't make her
useful ASAP, right?
困る[こまる]:to be troubled/to be worried/to be bothered
うちらも困るでしょ
I guess you're right. It's just a drop,
and Mr. Hoshino's with her.
落とす[おとす]:to drop|to clean off (dirt, makeup, paint, etc.)|to lose (a match)||, 一緒[いっしょ]:together|at the same time|same
そうですね 落とすだけですし
星野さんが一緒なら
プレート:plate (often as in "tectonic plate"), ぶつかる:to strike against/to collide with|to encounter, 衛星[えいせい]:satellite
（タナベ）それで プレートに
ぶつかる衛星って何なんですか？
So, what's this satellite that the plate
is gonna collide with?
Didn't you read
the mission profile?
資料[しりょう]:materials/data/document, 読む[よむ]:to read|to count|to guess
（ハチマキ）
お前は 資料 読んでないのか？
I didn't get
the mission profile!
資料[しりょう]:materials/data/document, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation, もらう:to receive/to take|to get somebody to do something
資料なんて もらってませんよ
Oh, you didn't?
It's INTO's Dario-14.
連合[れんごう]:union/alliance|RENGO (Japanese Trade Union Confederation)
（ハチマキ）ああ そうだっけか
連合のダリオ14だよ
確か[たしか]:sure|reliable|If I'm not mistaken
（タナベ）
ダリオ？ あっ それって確か…
Dario?
But isn't that a...
Yep, a military bird.
軍事[ぐんじ]:military affairs, 衛星[えいせい]:satellite
（ハチマキ）そう 軍事衛星
（タナベ）はっ
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 地球[ちきゅう]:the earth/the globe, 監視[かんし]:monitoring/watching/observation
（ハチマキ）
宇宙から地球を監視して―
It monitors the Earth
from space,
国[くに]:country|region|national government||, 悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing, 見張る[みはる]:to stand watch/to stand guard|to open one's eyes wide
どっかの国が 悪いことしてないか
見張ってんだと
...and keeps an eye out to see if some
country somewhere is misbehaving.
軍隊[ぐんたい]:armed forces/military/troops, 増やす[ふやす]:to increase/to add to/to augment
だから どっかが
軍隊を増やそうとしても―
So if some country tries to expand its military,
INTO will come storming in, right?
連合[れんごう]:union/alliance|RENGO (Japanese Trade Union Confederation), やってくる:to come along/to come around|to arrive at the present
すぐに連合がやってくるだろ？
They talk about keeping the peace and
liberation, but they're really just looking out for...
治安[ちあん]:public order, 治安[じあん]:Jian era (1021.2.2-1024.7.13), 維持[いじ]:maintenance/preservation/improvement, 解放[かいほう]:release/unleashing|deallocation (of computer memory)
治安維持とか
解放とか言ってっけど―
てめえ:you (used by young males)|oneself
本当んとこは てめえらの…
STOP!
ストップ:stop
（タナベ）ストップ！
（ハチマキ）なああっ…
（タナベ）あっ…
What the hell do you think you're doing?!
You rank amateur!
いきなり:abruptly/suddenly/all of a sudden
（ハチマキ）
いきなり何てことすんだ！
素人[しろうと, しろと]:amateur|respectable woman (not a prostitute, hostess, geisha, etc.)|unlicensed prostitute
このド素人！
But it's a military satellite, Senpai!
It's a tool for war!
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 軍事[ぐんじ]:military affairs, 衛星[えいせい]:satellite
（タナベ）
でも先輩 軍事衛星ですよ？
戦争[せんそう]:war, 道具[どうぐ]:tool/implement|means
戦争の道具じゃないですか！
We can't scrap a symbol of peace
to save something like that!
物[もの, もん]:thing|one's things|things||, 物[ぶつ, ブツ]:stock/products|stolen goods, 平和[へいわ]:peace/harmony, 平和[ピンフ, ピンホー]:concealed winning hand consisting of chows, a pair that isn't a value pair, and an open wait, 象徴[しょうちょう]:symbol, 廃棄[はいき]:disposal/abandonment|annulment, なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
そんな物のために
平和の象徴を廃棄するなんて
やがる:verb suffix indicating hatred and contempt, or disdain for another's action
（ハチマキ）何言ってやがる
What are you saying?
One's a functional satellite, and the other's
a plate that's just floating there!
動く[うごく]:to move|to operate|to be touched||, 衛星[えいせい]:satellite, 浮かぶ[うかぶ]:to float|to rise to surface|to come to mind, プレート:plate (often as in "tectonic plate")
動いている衛星と
浮かんでるだけのプレートだぞ
How can you
compare the two?!
比べもの[くらべもの]:something worthy of comparison/something being compared
比べものになるかっての！
比べる[くらべる]:to compare/to make a comparison|to compete
比べるまでもありません
There's nothing to compare!
Which is more important, peace or war?!
戦争[せんそう]:war, 平和[へいわ]:peace/harmony, 平和[ピンフ, ピンホー]:concealed winning hand consisting of chows, a pair that isn't a value pair, and an open wait, どっち:which way/which direction|which one (esp. of two alternatives), 大事[だいじ, おおごと]:important/valuable|safe (Tochigi dialect), なんて:how ..!/what ..!|what (questioning), なんて:such as/(things) like|exclamation
戦争と平和の
どっちが大事かなんて
Listen up!
We're debris collectors!
デブリ:debris, 屋[や]:(something) shop|somebody who sells (something) or works as (something)|somebody with a (certain) personality trait||
（ハチマキ）あのな
俺たちはデブリ屋なんだよ
We get rid of the plate as part
of our job, and that's that!
仕事[しごと]:work/job|work, プレート:plate (often as in "tectonic plate"), 廃棄[はいき]:disposal/abandonment|annulment
仕事として プレートを廃棄すりゃ
それでいいんだ！
Then the satellite ought to be hit
by the plate and be destroyed!
軍事[ぐんじ]:military affairs, 衛星[えいせい]:satellite
（タナベ）
だったら 軍事衛星だって―
プレート:plate (often as in "tectonic plate"), ぶつかる:to strike against/to collide with|to encounter, なくなる:to die, なくなる:to be lost (e.g. luggage)/to be missing|to be used up
プレートにぶつかって
なくなっちゃえばいいんです
（ハチマキ）何だと？ この
What the hell
are you saying?!
デブリ:debris, 増える[ふえる]:to increase/to multiply
そんなことしたら
デブリが増えちまうだろうが！
If we did that,
it'd just make more debris!
うわあ:Wow!/Holy smokes!/Aaargh!
（タナベ）
うわあっ うわああーっ…
H-Hey, wait!
ちょ ちょ ちょっと
ああっ… ああっ…
ああっ あっ…
溺れる[おぼれる]:to drown/to nearly drown|to indulge in
マジ お… 溺れる…
My feet...
I'm drowning!
Geez, at least learn
your suit's halt code!
ったく:good grief (expression of exasperation), 停止[ていし, ちょうじ]:suspension/interruption|suspension of music, dance, etc. as a sign of mourning for a prominent person, 信号[しんごう]:signal/signalling|traffic light, ぐらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that
（ハチマキ）ったく
停止信号ぐらい知っとけっての
仕事[しごと]:work/job|work
ほら 仕事やるぞ 仕事
Hey, we got work
to do!
Even if this is our job,
it's just not right!
いくら:how much?/how many?|even, 仕事[しごと]:work/job|work
（タナベ）
でも いくら仕事だからって―
おかしい:funny/amusing|strange
こんなの おかしいです
I thought astronauts were supposed to be free
of countries and gravity and all that other stuff!
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 飛行士[ひこうし]:pilot, 国[くに]:country|region|national government||, 重力[じゅうりょく]:gravity/gravitation/gravitational pull, 全部[ぜんぶ]:all/entire/whole, 自由[じゆう]:freedom/liberty/as it pleases you
宇宙飛行士って 国とか重力とか
全部 自由なんじゃないんですか？
偉い[えらい]:great/excellent|awful, 夢[ゆめ]:dream, 語る[かたる]:to talk about|to recite|to indicate
偉そうに 夢 語ってんじゃねえよ
Give the noble daydreams a rest,
you preachy rookie.
口先[くちさき]:lip service/mere words|lips, 新入り[しんいり]:newcomer/initiate/rookie
この口先だけの新入りが
Astronauts are wage slaves
just like any other!
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 飛行士[ひこうし]:pilot, サラリーマン:office worker/company employee/company man
宇宙飛行士だってな
サラリーマンなんだ！
It's because of that that everybody
calls you the Half Section!
半[はん]:half|half-past|odd number|, 課[か]:lesson|section (in an organization)|counter for lessons and chapters (of a book)
（タナベ）そんなんだから
半課とか言われちゃうんですよ
You've got to set
your goals higher!
もっと:(some) more/even more/longer, 志[こころざし]:will|kindness|gift (as a token of gratitude), 高い[たかい]:high/tall|expensive, 持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||
もっと 志を高く持って…
Complete!
コンプリート:complete
（ハチマキ）コンプリート
（タナベ）えっ？
Target point reached.
現地[げんち]:actual place/local/on-site, 到着[とうちゃく]:arrival
（ハチマキ）現地到着
連合[れんごう]:union/alliance|RENGO (Japanese Trade Union Confederation), マーク:mark/symbol/insignia
（タナベ）
でも これ 連合のマークですけど
But this is INTO's logo...
記念[きねん]:commemoration/celebration/honoring the memory of something, プレート:plate (often as in "tectonic plate")
（ハチマキ）
これが記念プレートだよ
This is the
memorial plate.
（タナベ）ん？ あっ…
"In 2055, peace was preserved in Mananga
through the efforts of INTO."
世界[せかい]:the world|sphere|renowned|, 連合[れんごう]:union/alliance|RENGO (Japanese Trade Union Confederation), 尽力[じんりょく]:efforts/exertion/endeavour
“2055年
世界連合の尽力により―”
平和[へいわ]:peace/harmony, 平和[ピンフ, ピンホー]:concealed winning hand consisting of chows, a pair that isn't a value pair, and an open wait, 維持[いじ]:maintenance/preservation/improvement
“マナンガの平和は維持された”
"An evil regime was opposed in order to
establish a foothold for freedom and justice..."
自由[じゆう]:freedom/liberty/as it pleases you, 正義[せいぎ]:justice/right/righteousness, 悪い[わるい]:bad|evil|unprofitable||, 悪い[にくい]:hateful/abominable|amazing, 大戦[たいせん]:great war/great battle, 対抗[たいこう]:opposition/antagonism
“自由と正義の橋頭保として
悪なる大戦に対抗し…”
紛争[ふんそう]:dispute/trouble/strife
（ハチマキ）
ケッ！ マナンガの紛争は―
Big talk, considering that they're the ones who
started the conflict in Mananga in the first place.
てめえ:you (used by young males)|oneself, 仕掛ける[しかける]:to start|to challenge|to set (traps)
てめえらが仕掛けたくせに
What the heck is this?
This is a symbol of peace?
平和[へいわ]:peace/harmony, 平和[ピンフ, ピンホー]:concealed winning hand consisting of chows, a pair that isn't a value pair, and an open wait, 象徴[しょうちょう]:symbol
何これ 平和の象徴？
This is just
INTO propaganda!
連合[れんごう]:union/alliance|RENGO (Japanese Trade Union Confederation), 宣伝[せんでん]:publicity/advertisement/advertising
ただの連合の宣伝じゃない
確か[たしか]:sure|reliable|If I'm not mistaken, 今更[いまさら]:now (after such a long time)/at this late hour (i.e. it is too late for something)|afresh, 回収[かいしゅう]:collection/recovery/withdrawal
（ハチマキ）確かに 今更
こんなもん 回収できねえよな
Well, it's true that they can't afford
to have this brought back, not now.
Hell, our country's in INTO now, too,
so I guess it can't be helped.
国[くに]:country|region|national government||
まっ 俺らの国も―
連合[れんごう]:union/alliance|RENGO (Japanese Trade Union Confederation)
連合に入ってんだから
しかたねえか？
（タナベ）すみませんでした
I'm sorry about what I said.
Please go ahead and drop this thing.
とっとと:quickly/at once/right away, 落とす[おとす]:to drop|to clean off (dirt, makeup, paint, etc.)|to lose (a match)||, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
とっとと 落としちゃってください
Hey, that's your job, too.
仕事[しごと]:work/job|work, でもある:to also be (formal, literary)/implies that as well as the earlier stated this is also the case|to be ... or something
（ハチマキ）
おい お前の仕事でもあるんだぞ
（タナベ）あっ…
Forget it. You just sit there.
You copy?
座る[すわる]:to sit|to assume (a position)|to hold steady
（ハチマキ）
もういい お前は座ってろ
コピー:copy/photocopy
ユー コピー？
アイ コピー
I copy...
DS-12, this is ISPV-7.
Please report operation status.
こちら:this way (direction close to the speaker or towards the speaker)/this direction|here (place close to the speaker or where the speaker is)
（クレア）DS-12 こちらISPV-７
作業[さぎょう]:work/operation/manufacturing, 状況[じょうきょう]:state of affairs (around you)/situation/circumstances, 報告[ほうこく]:report/information, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
作業状況 報告してください
フェーズ:phase, ナイン:nine, クリア:clear
（フィー）
フェーズナインまでクリア
We've cleared up through phase 9.
Standing by for de-orbit burn.
軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, 離脱[りだつ]:withdrawal/secession/separation, 噴射[ふんしゃ]:jet/spray/injection, 向ける[むける]:to turn towards/to point, 待機[たいき]:alert/standby/await an opportunity
軌道離脱噴射に向け 待機中
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
（タナベ）あの 先輩
Um... Senpai?
もう 15分たちましたけど
It's been 15 minutes.
We're way behind schedule.
予定[よてい]:plans/arrangement/schedule, とっく:a long time ago|quickly/swiftly, とっく:special ward|special economic zone (China), 過ぎる[すぎる]:to pass through|to pass (i.e. of time)|to have expired||, 過ぎる[よぎる]:to go by/to cross/to pass by
予定時間 とっくに過ぎちゃって…
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
あっ すいません
先輩がやるんですよね
Oh, I'm sorry. You're going to do it,
aren't you, Senpai?
新入り[しんいり]:newcomer/initiate/rookie
（ハチマキ）新入り
Rookie.
（タナベ）はい？
Yes?
Why'd you come
into space?
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space
（ハチマキ）
お前 なんで宇宙に来た？
（タナベ）えっ？
あ… あの…
Well, um... When I was getting close to
graduation time, I started to get curious.
卒業[そつぎょう]:graduation/completion (e.g. of a course)|outgrowing something, 近づく[ちかづく, ちかずく]:to approach/to draw near|to get acquainted with
卒業が近づいたとき―
私 なんか
知りたくなったんですよね
I wanted to learn
what my limits were.
活動[かつどう]:action/activity|movie (esp. during the silent movie period), 限界[げんかい]:limit/bound
自分の活動限界ってやつを
What kind of person I was.
How big a mark I could leave on the world.
どういう:somehow/how/in what way, 存在[そんざい]:existence/being
自分がどういう存在なのか―
口出し[くちだし]:interference/meddling/butting in, 可能[かのう]:potential/possible/practicable, 世界[せかい]:the world|sphere|renowned|
どこまでが自分の口出し可能な
世界なのかって
So I...
だから… あっ
宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space
でも 私って宇宙には…
But I guess I'm not
cut out for space...
What did I
come here for?
（タナベ）
私 何しに来たんだろう
何がしたかったんだろう
What did I hope
to accomplish?
結局[けっきょく]:after all|conclusion|ending of a game of Go, つま先[つまさき]:toes/tips of the toes/toe of a shoe, sock, etc., 地球人[ちきゅうじん]:earthling/earthman, 確認[かくにん]:confirmation/verification/validation
結局 つま先まで地球人だって
確認しただけ
All I did was prove that I'm earthbound
right down to the core.
Tanabe.
聞こえる[きこえる]:to be heard/to be audible|to be said to be
（フィー）
タナベ タナベ 聞こえる？
Tanabe, you read me?
フィー:phi
（タナベ）フィーさん？
Fee-san?
落ちる[おちる]:to fall down|to be omitted|to decrease||, プレート:plate (often as in "tectonic plate")
（フィー）
落ちていくプレートを見てみな
Watch the plate
as it's going down.
（タナベ）えっ？
Pretty...
きれい:pretty/lovely|clean
きれい
子供たち[こどもたち]:children
（フィー）マナンガの子供たちも
それを見てる
The children of Mananga
are seeing that.
あっ…
コース:course (route, trail, course of study, course of action, plan, option)
（フィー）このコースなら―
The course it's on should
take it right over Mananga.
ちょうど:exactly/precisely|as if, ちょうど:supplies/furniture/fixtures, 真上[まうえ]:just above/right overhead, 通る[とおる]:to go by|to run (between)|to go indoors||
ちょうど
マナンガの真上を通るはずよ
天候[てんこう]:weather, さぞかし:certainly/surely, きれい:pretty/lovely|clean, 見える[みえる]:to be seen|to look|to come, 見える[まみえる]:to have an audience|to face (an enemy)|to serve (esp. as one's wife)
今日の天候なら さぞかし
きれいに見えるでしょうね
And with their weather today, they should
have a nice, clear view of it.
If it can bring happiness
to the children of Mananga,
作る[つくる]:to make|to prepare (food)|to raise||, 思惑[おもわく]:expectation|purpose|others' opinions of one|, 思惑[しわく]:perceptive mental disturbances
作った人の思惑は どうであれ―
...even if only for a brief moment, regardless of
the ulterior motives of the people who built it,
たとえ:example|simile/metaphor, たとえ:even if/no matter (what)/if, 一瞬[いっしゅん]:instant/moment/for an instant
たとえ一瞬でも―
子供たち[こどもたち]:children, 幸せ[しあわせ, しやわせ]:happiness/good fortune/luck
マナンガの子供たちが
幸せになれるのなら―
あんな:such (about something or someone distant from both speaker and listener, or about a situation unfamiliar to both speaker and listener)/so/that, あんな:Anna or Anwa era (968.8.13-970.3.25), デブリ:debris, 価値[かち]:value/worth/merit
あんなデブリにも
価値があったと思わない？
...even a piece of debris like that
has some value, don't you think?
以上[いじょう]:not less than|beyond ... (e.g. one's means)|above-mentioned||
（タナベ）このために
15分以上 待ってくれたんですか
You waited for more than 15 minutes
so you could do this?
んっ…
新入り[しんいり]:newcomer/initiate/rookie
（ハチマキ）新入り
（タナベ）はい
Rookie.
Y-Yes, sir?
帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home, コピー:copy/photocopy
（ハチマキ）ToyBoxに帰るぞ
ユー コピー？
We're heading back to Toy Box.
You copy?
コピー:copy/photocopy
あっ アイ コピーです！
I copy!
こちら:this way (direction close to the speaker or towards the speaker)/this direction|here (place close to the speaker or where the speaker is), フェーズ:phase, クリア:clear
（フィー）ISPV-７へ こちらDS-12
フェーズクリア
ISPV-7, this DS-12
Phase clear.
DS-12, this is Seven.
こちら:this way (direction close to the speaker or towards the speaker)/this direction|here (place close to the speaker or where the speaker is), セブン:seven
（クレア）DS-12へ こちらセブン
軌道[きどう]:orbit|railroad track|(on the right) track, クリアランス:clearance, 確認[かくにん]:confirmation/verification/validation
ダリオ14の
軌道クリアランスを確認
Dario-14 orbital clearance confirmed.
Mission complete.
ミッション:mission, コンプリート:complete
ミッション コンプリート
コピー:copy/photocopy
（フィー）アイ コピー
I copy. Now engaging return mode
to head back to Seven.
セブン:seven, 帰島[きとう]:return to an island, モード:mode (musical mode, mode of probability distribution, state of physical system), 移る[うつる]:to move (house)|to change the target of interest or concern|to elapse (passage of time)||
これより
セブンへの帰島モードに移る
ハチマキ:headband, 先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
（タナベ）ハチマキ先輩
Hachimaki-senpai! What do you mean,
"Special Excess Allowance"?!
特別[とくべつ]:special, 超過[ちょうか]:excess/being more than, 手当て[てあて]:salary|medical care|advance preparation, どういう:somehow/how/in what way
特別超過手当てって
どういうことですか？
うるせえなあ
Give it a rest!
If you're out in space for longer than your
maximum time allowed, you get extra pay!
規定[きてい]:stipulation/prescription/provision, 以上[いじょう]:not less than|beyond ... (e.g. one's means)|above-mentioned||, 宇宙[うちゅう]:universe/cosmos/space, 手当て[てあて]:salary|medical care|advance preparation, 付く[つく]:to be attached|to remain imprinted|to bear (fruit, interest, etc.)||, 付く[づく]:to become (a state, condition, etc.)
規定時間以上 宇宙に出てると
手当てが付くんだよ
You got paid, too,
didn't you?
付く[つく]:to be attached|to remain imprinted|to bear (fruit, interest, etc.)||, 付く[づく]:to become (a state, condition, etc.)
お前にも付いてただろ？
そんなことのために
15分も待ってたんですか？
Is that why you waited
for more than 15 minutes?!
他[ほか]:other (place, thing, person)|outside|nothing except|, 他[た]:other (esp. people and abstract matters), どんな:what/what kind of|(with -temo, demo, etc.) any(body, thing, means, etc.), 理由[りゆう, わけ]:reason/pretext/motive
他にどんな理由があるよ？
What other reason
would there be?
子供たち[こどもたち]:children, 希望[きぼう]:hope/wish/aspiration, 流れ星[ながれぼし]:shooting star/falling star|star (white patch on the forehead of a horse)
だから マナンガの子供たちに
希望っていう名の流れ星を―
You mean you didn't do it to give the children of Mananga a shooting star of hope as a present?!
プレゼント:present/gift
プレゼントしたんじゃ
ないんですか？
おむつ:diaper/nappy/napkin
あ？ 何くっせーこと言ってんだ
このおむつ女
What's that sap you're spouting,
diaper girl?
おっ
おむつ:diaper/nappy/napkin, 偉い[えらい]:great/excellent|awful, くださる:to give/to confer|to kindly do for one
おむつ男が
偉そうに言わないでください！
Don't you talk down to me,
diaper boy!
Is that any way to talk
to your sepmai?!
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 向かう[むかう]:to face|to go towards/to head towards
お前 先輩に向かって
Senpai doesn't make a difference!
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder, 後輩[こうはい]:junior (at work, school, etc.)/younger people/younger student
先輩も後輩もありません
Give your superior enough time
to have a smoke in peace, okay?
- Don't you have any tact in you?!
上司[じょうし]:superior authorities/boss, 一服[いっぷく]:(a) dose/(a) puff/(a) smoke, ぐらい:approximately/about|to (about) the extent that, 静か[しずか]:quiet|slow|calm
（フィー）
上司が一服してるときぐらい
静かにしてよね
- Then stop pointing
your finger at people!
指さす[ゆびさす]:to point at
（ハチマキ）人を指さすな
（タナベ）ああ いや すいません
Oh. Sorry about that...
But those two things are...
でも それとこれとは…
（ハチマキ）違うってのか おい
Totally different?
決まる[きまる]:to be decided/to be settled|to look good in (clothes)
（タナベ）
違うに決まってるじゃないですか
Of course they are!
Don't you get it, Senpai?!
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
分かんないんですか？ 先輩
Who do you think you are,
you rookie?!
新入り[しんいり]:newcomer/initiate/rookie
（ハチマキ）
何だと？ この 新入りが！
♪～
gutto mizu wo nomihoshi
We gulp down some water
飲み干す[のみほす]:to drink up/to drain (cup)
♪グッと水を飲み干し
yuuyakegumo miageru no sa
and look up at the evening clouds.
夕焼け[ゆうやけ]:evening glow/red sunset/afterglow (of sunset), 雲[くも]:cloud, 見上げる[みあげる]:to look up at/to raise one's eyes|to look up to
♪夕焼け雲見上げるのさ
kyou mo ichinichi ga owatte
Let's wind our way home under the roadside trees as another day ends.
一[いち]:one|best|first||, 一[ひとつ]:one|for one thing|only||, 終わる[おわる]:to finish/to end/to close
♪今日も一日が終わって
gairoju no shita wo kaerou
街路樹[がいろじゅ]:roadside trees, 帰る[かえる]:to return|to leave|to get home
♪街路樹の下を帰ろう
yaru koto darake de tenpatte
Even if life's so hectic that our tempers flare,
だらけ:implying (negatively) that something is full of (e.g. mistakes)|covered all over (e.g. with blood), テンパる:to become one tile away from completion|to be at one's wits' end/to be about to blow one's fuse
♪やることだらけで
テンパって、
muri wo shite tsumazuite mo
we push ourselves too hard, and we stumble,
無理[むり]:unreasonable|impossible|forcible||, つまずく:to stumble/to trip|to fail
♪無理をして、
つまずいても
nani ka kanarazu tsukanderu sa
I know there'll be something to grab hold of.
必ず[かならず]:always/without exception/necessarily, つかむ:to seize/to catch|to obtain
♪何か必ず
つかんでるさ
kiraku ni ikou ze
Let's move on without a care in our hearts.
気楽[きらく]:carefree/comfortable|easygoing
♪気楽にいこうぜ
素晴らしい[すばらしい, すんばらしい]:wonderful/splendid/magnificent, 人生[じんせい]:(human) life (i.e. conception to death)
♪素晴らしい人生だから
subarashii jinsei dakara
It's a wonderful life.
愛する[あいする]:to love, 勇気[ゆうき]:courage/bravery/valour, 持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||
♪自分を愛する
勇気を持とう
jibun wo aisuru yuuki wo motou
So let's have the courage to love ourselves.
atarashii doa tataite
Let's take it one step at a time,
新しい[あたらしい]:new/novel/fresh, 叩く[たたく]:to strike|to play drums|to abuse||, 叩く[はたく]:to dust|to slap|to use up money
♪新しいドア叩いて
hitotsu hitotsu aruite yukou
knocking on new doors on the way.
歩く[あるく]:to walk
♪ひとつひとつ歩いてゆこう
subarashii jinsei na no sa
It's a wonderful life.
素晴らしい[すばらしい, すんばらしい]:wonderful/splendid/magnificent, 人生[じんせい]:(human) life (i.e. conception to death)
♪素晴らしい人生なのさ
kimi mo boku mo subete no hito mo
You and I and everyone else
♪君も僕もすべての人も
yorokobi to kanashimi no imi
Keep on searching for the meaning
喜び[よろこび]:joy/delight/rapture, 悲しみ[かなしみ]:sadness/sorrow|affection, 意味[いみ]:meaning/significance
♪喜びと悲しみの意味
sagashitsuzukete so just on my way
Of joy and sadness, so just on my way.
探す[さがす]:to search (for something desired, needed)/to look for|to search (for something lost), つづける:to continue/to keep up/to keep on
♪探しつづけて
so just on my way
Next Time
Like a Dream
何なんですか？ それ
What's that?
"Idea Notebook for Obtaining a Spaceship of My Own."
宇宙船[うちゅうせん]:space ship, 獲得[かくとく]:acquisition/possession, 構想[こうそう]:plan/plot/idea, ノート:notebook/copy-book/exercise book
（ユーリ）マイ宇宙船
獲得構想ノート
はい？
Excuse me?
入社[にゅうしゃ]:joining a company/getting a job with a company/entering a company, 持つ[もつ]:to hold (in one's hand)|to possess|to maintain||, らしい:seeming ... (expresses judgment based on evidence, reason or trustworthy hearsay)/appearing ...|-ish
（フィー）入社する前から
持ってたらしいよ
Apparently, he had it even before he joined the company.
先輩[せんぱい]:senior (at work or school)/superior/elder
（タナベ）あっ 先輩！
Senpai!
This is one time when running away or failing isn't an option!
今回[こんかい]:now/this time/lately, ばかり:only/merely|approximately, 逃げ[にげ]:escape/getaway/evasion, 負け[まけ]:defeat/loss/losing (a game), 許す[ゆるす]:to permit|to exempt (from fine)|to confide in|
（ハチマキ）今回ばかりは
逃げも負けも許されねえ
It ain't an option!
許す[ゆるす]:to permit|to exempt (from fine)|to confide in|
許されねえんだよ！
Can I really do it...?
（ハチマキ）
できるのか？ 本当に